Johnson, Cyril Woolen Company Graphics 6589 G
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Cyril Johnson Woolen Company Graphics
1927-1954
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Cyril Johnson Woolen Company.
6589 G
2.67 cubic feet
2.7 linear ft.
Paintings (Visual works), watercolors (paintings), graphics.
Artwork of millworkers by K. Stephens. Also, loose newspaper clippings of advertisements and scrapbooks containing newspaper and periodical advertisements, mostly menswear.; cloth samples (swatches) appear in many ads.
10261364
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183 kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel-center
Compiled by:
R. Miles, February 15, 2018
EAD encoding:
Marcie Farwell, October 09, 2019
Biographical / Historical
The company, started in 1879, was located in Stafford Springs, Conn., with selling offices on Madison Ave., New York. It manufactured fine wool suitings and overcoatings. The company was sold in 1963. During the period covered by this collection, it operated 10 sets of cards, 100 looms, and 4,000 spindles.
Scope and Contents
Artwork of millworkers by K. Stephens. Also, loose newspaper clippings of advertisements and scrapbooks containing newspaper and periodical advertisements, mostly menswear, for the company's cloth and products made from it, 1927-1954; cloth samples (swatches) appear in many ads.
Custodial History
American Textile History Museum Collection, gift of the Cyril Johnson Woolen Company.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Related Materials
Related Collections: 6589 F: Cyril Johnson Woolen Company Films 6589: Cyril Johnson Woolen Company Records 6589 P: Cyril Johnson Woolen Company Photographs
Carding-machines; Dyes and dyeing; Women employees; Male employees; Looms; Textile fabrics; Textile factories; Textile industry; Textile industry--Connecticut; Textile machinery; Textile workers; Weaving; Winding machines; Women textile workers; Woolen and worsted manufacture; Stafford Springs (Conn.); Crompton & Knowles Loom Works.; Cyril Johnson Woolen Company.; Davis & Furber Machine Co.
10261364
- Men processing wool, Artwork (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Item 1: Men sorting wool, Cyril Johnson Woolen Company, Stafford Springs, CT, Graphics (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Scope and Contents
    Robert K. Stephens, artist. Watercolor, ca. 1942-1944. Image depicts two older men sorting wool at the Cyril Johnson Woolen Company. Men stand at table sorting wool, while baskets loaded with raw wool are everywhere in the room. Clock on wall reads 3:55 p.m. Signed "R. Stephens" in the lower right-hand corner. 61 x 47.5 cm..
- Men dyeing wool, Artwork (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Item 1: Men working at dye vats, Cyril Johnson Woolen Company, Stafford Springs, CT, 1943; Graphics (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Robert K. Stephens, artist. Watercolor, 1943. Image depicts men working at dye vats at the Cyril Johnson Woolen Company. The men are stock dyeing by hand. The man in the foreground appears to be either removing or inserting wool into a large dye vat; the man in the center ground may be doing the same or may be stirring the dye vat. Another man watches from the background, while another stands in the left background. Signed "Robert K. Stephens '43" in the lower right-hand corner. 61 x 51.25 cm..
- Spool room, Artwork (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Item 1: Card room, Cyril Johnson Woolen Company, Stafford Springs, CT, Graphics (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Robert K. Stephens, artist, Watercolor, ca. 1942-1944. Image depicts view of the card room at the Cyril Johnson Woolen Company. One man operates a woolen card with the tape condenser at the end in the foreground, while another man can be seen working at a carding machine behind him. Signed "R. Stephens," barely visible in lower right-hand corner. 59.75 x 47.25 cm..
- Fabric room, Artwork (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Item 1: Weave room, Cyril Johnson Woolen Company, Stafford Springs, CT, Graphics (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Robert K. Stephens, artist. Watercolor, ca. 1942-1944. Image depicts the weave room at the Cyril Johnson Woolen Company. The room is filled with looms; two male employees can be seen at the looms, which are Crompton & Knowles power looms (probably W-3s). "R. Stephens" signed in the lower center edge. Matted. 61.25 x 47 cm..
- Fabric room, Artwork (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Item 1: Shearing machine for woolen cloth, Cyril Johnson Woolen Company, Stafford Springs, CT, Graphics (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Robert K. Stephens, artist. Watercolor, ca. 1942-1944. Image depicts a view of a shearing machine for shearing woolen cloth in the Cyril Johnson Woolen Company. A male employee operates the shearing machine; piled cloth is seen to the left. Shearing is the process for woolens and worsteds of mechanically cutting or trimming the projecting fibers from the surface of cloth. Signed "R. Stephens" in the lower left-hand corner. 60.5 x 47 cm..
- "The United States Navy At War" (Box 1, Folder 6)
  3 copies
  - Item 1: Semper Paratus, Graphics (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Number One of a Series: "The U.S. Coast Guard At War".
  - Item 2: Sub-Busting, Graphics (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Number Two of a Series: "The U.S. Coast Guard At War".
  - Item 3: Convoy Duty, Graphics (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Number Three of a Series: "The U.S. Coast Guard At War".
  - Item 4: Aviation Patrol, Graphics (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Number Four of a Series: "The U.S. Coast Guard At War".
  - Item 5: Battle of the Atlantic, Graphics (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Number Five of a Series: "The U.S. Coast Guard At War".
- Assorted Magazine Advertisements (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Assorted Magazine Advertisements on display boards (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Advertisement sketch (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Assorted news clippings - showing advertisements (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Resolutions Congratulating J.P. Stevens and Co., Inc. on the Occasion of the 150th Anniversary of its Founding (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Advertising/Sample booklets (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Presenting the story of the making of Worsted and Wool Fabrics (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Guilford District Checks (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Cyril Johnson - Newspaper Ads, 1927-1928 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Cyril Johnson - Newspaper Ads, 1928-1931 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Assorted publications: related to fabric production (Box 3, Folder 1)
  Barks' Parables; Connecticut Progress Exhibit; Fine Woolens in the making; Nylaine: A Story of the Development of a Fabric / by Carroll D. Newell; Five Star Fabrics for 1940-1941; Concerning Coverts; Connecticut Circle: the Story of Stafford
- Correspondence (Box 3, Folder 2)
- News clippings showing advertisements (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Assorted advertisements (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Advertisements, fabric samples and small sample booklets (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Miscellaneous (Box 3, Folder 6)
  Howard Bros. Mfg. Co, Roving Weight in Grains When Spinning Draft (card giving fabric specifications)
- Cyril Johnson: Magazine Advertisements (in a binder), 1941-1954 (Box 4, Folder 1)
- Cyril Johnson: Magazine Advertisements (in a binder), 1942-1954 (Box 4, Folder 2)